# Suresh CHINNA SHANMUGAM

# Big Data Consultant, Data Science, Data Analyst & Tableau Designer, RPA Technical Architect, Digital Technology Manager

16 Avenue Émile Baudot, 91120, Palaiseau, France

Mobile: +33 758 07 2207 Email: suresh.cs0524@gmail.com Websites: Tableau, Github



# Summary

I bring a dynamic 15-year IT career to the table, including 3 years as a Big Data engineer, Tableau Data visualization and RPA Technical Architect experience. In addition to 5 years of IT delivery management experience and worked as digital technology Associate manager at Accenture. Strong Enterprise application development experience in C++, Java, Python, ML, Data analytics & visualization skills in tableau and others. I worked in multi-geographical locations in the United States (8 years) and India (7), with year-on-year success in technology, solutions, and consulting services. 10 years of experience in retail and supply chain, as well as 4 years in banking, finance, and telecommunications. Python API, REST APIs, Big Data, Hadoop, HDFS, Yarn Map Reduce, Flume, Apache Spark, Scala, and other technologies are among my strong suits.

## **Education**

## **Paris School of Business**

Paris, FRANCE

MBA (Master of Business Administration)

July 2021

• Specialization in Digital Marketing Strategy and Data Analytics

## **Jawaharlal Nehru Technological University**

Hyderabad, INDIA

Bachelor of Technology

2004

Specialization in Computer Science & Systems Engineering

# **Professional Experience**

Accenture Bangalore, INDIA

Big data Engineer, Data Analyst & Tableau Designer, Architect & Technology Manager Nov. 2018 – Jan. 2020

- Big Data Engineer & Technical Architect for SOX (Sarbanes-Oxley Act) Audit and Compliance system
   @BESBTUY Retail Client
- Data Analyst, Tableau designer and Data Visualization expert for SOX system @BESTBUY Retail client
- Solution Design and Development of Web & Enterprise application using JAVA & J2EE Technologies.
- Hands on experience in Core Java, Servlets, JSP, JDBC, Spring, Hibernate, Tomcat web servers, JBOSS web servers
- Big Data Ecosystems: HDFS, Map Reduce, YARN, Hive, Pig, HBase, Oozie, Apache Spark, Scala

Accenture Minneapolis, USA

From Technical Lead to Associate Delivery Manager, RPA Technical Architect

Sep. 2010 - Nov. 2018

- Delivery Head, Functional and Technical Architect of Retek Sales Audit ReSA @BESTBUY Retail client
- Delivery Head, Functional and Technical Architect of Retek Invoice Matching ReIM @BESTBUY Retail
- Functional and Technical SME for Retek Merchandising System RMS@BESTBUY Retail client
- RPA (Robotic Process Automation) Blue Prism Technical Architect @BESBTUY Retail Client
- RPA Head of Centre of Excellence @BESTBUY Retail Client
- Big Data Engineer & Technical Architect for SOX (Sarbanes-Oxley Act) Audit and Compliance system
   @BESBTUY Retail Client

Accenture Bangalore, INDIA

From Associate Software Engineer to Technical Lead

Mar. 2005 - Sep. 2010

- C++ Developer, ISIX system Image Share and Exchange @Bank of America Financial /Banking Client
- Sr Analyst Developer, LESOG Local Exchange Service Order Generator @AT&T Telecom Client
- Technical Lead, POS Point of Sale @BESTBUY Retail Client

# **Languages, Skills & Certifications**

### Languages:

English- Fluent
 French: Basic (learning in progress)

#### **Core Competencies:**

• Primary Skills : PRO\*C (Expert), C, C++ (Expert), Core Java

- Big Data Ecosystems: HDFS, Map Reduce, YARN, Hive, HBase, Apache Spark, Scala, Kafka
- Data Visualization & Analytics Tools: Tableau, SAS, IBM SPSS
- Python: Python Programming (Advanced), Python API Flask-RESTFul, Django, REST-API
- Al, Machine Learning | Deep Learning: Python, Pytorch, TensorFlow/Keras, Scikit-learn, pandas, and other ML/DL libraries, Kubernetes
- Data Bases: Elastic Search | MySQL | NoSQL | Oracle SQL, PL/SQL (Expert) | Postgre | MongoDB
- Robotic Process Automation (RPA): Blue Prism (Expert), UI Path (Advanced)

#### **Technical Skills:**

- OS: HP Unix (Expert), IBM AIX, Linux (Advanced), Windows
- CI/CD & DevOps: Jenkins, Git; Servers: Tomcat, JBOSS; Scripting Languages: Shell | Perl-Expert
- Debugging Tools: GDB, Web Services: (AXIS2C) | Code Quality, Eclipse, Putty
- Cloud: AWS Cloud Practitioner | Google Cloud
- Schedular/Automation: Maestro | cronjobs | RPA schedule management | DB schedulers
- Version Control Tools: CVS | Harvest | PVCS | SVN Tortoise | VSTS/Microsoft Azure | GIT Hub.

#### **Project Management Skills:**

Tools: Project Libre, Trello

## **IT & Management Certifications**

- Blue Prism Certified Developer, Solution Designer & Architect (AD01, ASD01, ATA02, ARA01) —BluePrism
   Developer, Solution Designer, Technical Architect, ROM Architect
- Accenture: PTL Pathway to Leadership
- Coursera: Google Cloud Platform Fundamentals & Big Data and Machine Learning
- Coursera: Programming for Everybody (Python), University of Michigan

# **MBA Student Project - Capstone**

 Research study on Blockchain and Artificial Intelligence in Supply chain and logistics to Increase Transparency and efficiency

# **Professional Experience Summary**

- 3+ years of Robotic process automation (RPA) Development experience in Blue Prism, as Certified Blue Prism Technical Architect, solutioned and developed multiple automation workstreams such as Customer order creation, Invoice creation, employee support, Price support, sale & returns order bot process. 2.8 years exp in python and worked as data analyst roles for the audit system.
- 3+ years of DevOps, Web & Enterprise application development experience using JAVA & J2EE
  Technologies and hands on exp Hands on experience in Core Java, Servlets, JSP, JDBC, Spring, Hibernate,
  Tomcat web servers, JBOSS web servers. Adept in Enterprise Architecture, End-to-End Business Analysis.
- Headed Center of Excellence (COE) and end-to-end execution of project delivery & generated multimillion-dollar programs of software / application development projects as per SLAs and balancing work distribution to meet preset deliverables.
- Well verse with Object Oriented Analysis and Design, proficient in developing client server, web and enterprise applications using C++, Java, Perl & Python and RPA (Robotic process Automation) Blueprism technology. Experienced work with Waterfall, Agile, Lean and/or Continuous Delivery approaches and best practices, such as Continuous Integration, TDD, BDD.

## **Interests & Achievements**

#### Accenture

- STEP UP program: Mentored High School Students in the twin cities
- BEST PREP Program: Participant in eMentor ship program for the Ubah medical academy students
- ACE (Accenture Excellence) award for leadership and people development activities.

#### **Trainings**

• SonarQube, Microsoft Azure DevOps, RPA Technologies on UiPath and Automation Anywhere

#### Interests

• Playing Sports: Cricket & Badminton